Are you prepared for the unexpected?
What happens tomorrow if you lost your
job? Would you have to go back to work?
Could you retire? What do things look
like? Every single Canadian should have
that answer once you're about 5 to 10
years from retirement. So, in this
video, I want to break down things that
you should be looking at, considering as
you get closer to retirement to make
sure that you're protected. There's some
new data out there that says that 56%
more than half of you that retire before
65 are forced into it. Is involuntary.
So, meaning that as much as we can plan
ahead and say, "Well, I want to retire
at 60 and here's everything how it's
going to go and all that," that that's
actually not going to be the case for
more than 50% of you, which is a scary
thought. So, my question to you is,
you're 55, you plan to retire at 60, and
two years from now, you get the pink
slip. Time to move out. We're
reorganizing. You're gone.
Are you able to retire or do you need to
work a little bit longer? And if you
need to work longer, how much longer and
how much more money do you have to
accumulate to get to your retirement
number? I've said it for many years. As
you get closer to retirement, you want a
retirement plan. People always ask like,
when is a good time to get a plan? And I
would say 5 years plus or minus. So 5 to
10 years, let's call it, is a great time
to have a retirement plan down. Why is
that? Well, you have a bit of a runway.
Where should I be saving my money?
Create tax strategy. A lot of you are
saving only to RRSPs, so you don't have
TFSAs as you enter retirement. So,
there's a lot of these gaps as you get
to retirement, but it gives you that
clear road map of, yeah, I'm on track. I
can retire at this date. Here's how much
money, but here's the side thing, and I
tell every client this. It also shows
you if you get laid off tomorrow, if
you're going to be okay, do you have to
go back to work, can you retire? Those
are big factors and those are big
questions and they're answers that you
should have once you're inside about 5
years from retirement. Now, you might
say, Adam, I'm never going to get laid
off. That's fine. then get a plan done a
little bit earlier to know could you
retire earlier? Could you have more
money in retirement? There's other side
benefits. But for most of you, you don't
have a plan until you're actually
walking into retirement. You have a
loose idea and you know the financial
planner at the bank's giving you two
thumbs up, but you don't know the actual
numbers to the point where we meet with
a lot of people that say, "I want to
retire in six months." We told them,
"Yeah, you could have retired two or
three years ago." Like, you're more than
okay. And they didn't know that. They've
never been told that because they didn't
do pre-planning. And so for all of you
that are getting close to retirement, my
question would be, can you retire when
you think you can? Where is your money
coming from? How does your whole picture
look like? And if you got laid off
tomorrow, do you have to go find a new
job or could you pack it in? The other
factor you need to look at is your
health. Maybe you plan to work for
another 5 years, but your health is
telling you otherwise. You may have a
health thing come up that forces you to
stop working. What does that look like?
There's other financial things that can
hit you a bit later in life too, right?
Like as you get closer to retirement,
guess what your parents are doing?
They're getting older as well and
they're maybe in a care facility or they
need more care from you and thus you
have to peel back from your time. And
again, I've had family members like
this. I've had friends, we've had
clients where I want to keep working,
but I have to scale back to four or
three or maybe two days a week. How does
that affect your plan? Again, run this
with your financial planner to see what
it looks like. And this is why I think
it's really important to have a
financial planner on your side working
with you, understanding your plan so
that you can run these things as they
come up. So maybe it's I'm 55, I plan to
retire at 60. Oh, I have an aging parent
that needs some help. Am I able to take
Fridays off? Like could I financially do
that? Again, you have to make sure your
company allows you to do that, but
financially, could you do that? Is it
setting you back from your retirement?
Like, yeah, you can take two days a week
off, but you're going to have to work
one year longer. Okay, that's fine. and
I want to take care of my aging parents.
I'm okay to work one year longer to only
work 3 days a week now to be able to
help them out. That's a sacrifice I'm
willing to make. I'm fine with that. But
you've run the numbers. You know what it
looks like. And on the flip side, as you
get close to retirement, if you have
kids, what's happening with them? Well,
they're coming back into the home. A lot
of them, right? A lot of them have moved
out and it's coming back home,
especially in BC and Ontario where they
can't afford real estate. Hey, mom, dad,
we need help. How are we helping them?
Okay. Yeah, let's let's help them with a
down payment on a, you know, condo or
townhouse or whatever. How does that
affect our plan? How much longer do we
have to work to help our kids out with a
little bit of money? So, again, these
are factors and these are conversations
a lot and I mean, a lot of Canadians are
having nowadays, whether it's with the
parents or with the kids, these
conversations are happening. So, if you
haven't had them yet, expect to have
them in the very near future. And again,
how does this play into? And that's why
when you sit down with your financial
planner, understand the flexibility of
your plan. Could I retire early? Could I
scale back to two or three days a week?
Could we help our kids? And if we can,
where does that money come from? How do
we do tax efficiency around that? So my
message to all of you watching this is
focus on control, not crisis. What can
you control? You can't control if you
get laid off, if you have health issues,
all of that, right? But you can control
the planning. What does it look like? If
this happened, what does it look like?
What if? What if? What if? And not that
you want to run a million whatifs with
your financial planner. A, it'll drive
you crazy. B, it'll drive them crazy.
But if I got laid off tomorrow, am I
going to be okay? Do I have to work? How
much longer do I have to work? What kind
of job? Maybe you get laid off. You're
like, perfect. I've always wanted to go
work at the bowling alley for two days a
week. Should that suffice? Is that going
to be enough money? Right? You have
these vocational things you want to do.
But again, so many of you as you get
closer to retirement, more than 50% of
you will be forced into retirement. What
does that look like for you? Have you
thought about that? I can guarantee you
most of you have not. Most clients that
hire our firm to do a retirement plan
are either walking into retirement or
months away. I encourage everyone reach
out 5 years away. Get a runaway plan.
Know what you're doing the next 5 years.
Kind of maybe you can retire earlier.
Maybe you can have way more for
retirement. Maybe you can do things
differently. Maybe you don't need to
save as much as you're saving right now.
So you could actually start enjoying
like a pre-retirement now and traveling
or doing whatever you want to do and not
have to wait five more years or 10 more
years, right? So getting a plan ahead,
knowing what to do, it creates that
peace of mind of if I get laid off
tomorrow, I know exactly what happens.
But it also gives you a clear timeline
on when you can retire, how much money
is going to come out, can I retire
early, do I have to keep working later?
All these things are answered in a
proper retirement plan. And if you're
wondering what does a full retirement
plan look like? Like how do we build out
a plan? How do we create efficiency and
make sure everything's working together
and not look at stuff in silos? We have
a full video breaking down how our team
builds out retirement plans for
Canadians like yourself.